{"tossups": [{"question": "A 1911 revolt in this city's Wuchang district led to the Xinhai [[SHIN-\"HIGH\"]] Revolution, which ended the Qing [[CHING]] Dynasty. One preliminary attack on this city was repelled in the \"Two-Eighteen Air Battle.\" The Nationalist government moved its primary operations to this city after the fall of Nanjing. After a four-month long battle, this city fell to the Japanese in 1938. For ten points, name this historical transportation hub and \"Chicago of China\" where the coronavirus that caused the COVID-19 pandemic was first discovered.", "answer": "<b><u>Wuhan</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This man attempted to have his cadets punished after they drew caricatures of him with the nickname \"square box\" due to his exceptionally large shoe size. The preserved hide of this man's horse, Little Sorrel, is on display at the Virginia Military Institute, where this man once taught. This general died from pneumonia brought upon by his amputation after he was shot by friendly fire at the Battle of Chancellorsville. For ten points, name this Confederate general who earned his famous nickname due to his heroics at Bull Run.", "answer": "Thomas \"Stonewall\" <b><u>Jackson</u></b> (or Thomas Jonathan <b><u>Jackson</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "In 2020, DNA paternity tests revealed that one holder of this position had fathered a child out of wedlock with Sybille de Selys Longchamps. The first holder of this position declined to take up the throne of Greece under the 1830 London Protocol. One man who took this title in 2013 resides at the Palace of Laeken [[LAY-kehn]] and claimed this title after the sudden abdication of his father, Albert II. For ten points, name this title, once held by a man who was known for atrocities committed in the Congo Free State, Leopold II.", "answer": "<b><u>King</u></b> of <b><u>Belgium</u></b> (or <b><u>King</u></b> of the <b><u>Belgians</u></b>; or <b><u>Koning</u></b> der <b><u>Belgen</u></b>; or <b><u>Roi</u></b> des <b><u>Belges</u></b>; or <b><u>K\u00f6nig</u></b> der <b><u>Belgier</u></b>; accept synonyms such as \"monarch\" or \"ruler\" in place of \"king\")", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Due most likely to the docking of the SS Talune, over 90 percent of this region's residents became infected with the Spanish Flu. A proposed colonial flag for this region featured three white palm trees on a red shield. This region's second civil war ended with the Tripartite Convention of 1899, which divided administration of this region between Germany and the United States. For ten points, name this region that contained the last colonial acquisition of the German Empire and the only U.S. territory south of the equator.", "answer": "<b><u>Samoa</u></b> (or Independent State of <b><u>Samoa</u></b>; or Malo Sa\u02bboloto Tuto\u02bbatasi o <b><u>S\u0101moa</u></b>; accept American <b><u>Samoa</u></b>; accept German <b><u>Samoa</u></b>; accept Deutsch <b><u>Samoa</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "A building named for this man had to sand down panels on the Founders Room to avoid concentrating sunlight on nearby residences. Acoustic designers Minoru Nagata and Yasuhisa Toyota created the interior of that building named for this man, whose exterior architecture was designed by Frank Gehry and which is the home of the Los Angeles Philharmonic. Another complex named after this man contains long-running sections such as Critter Country, Adventureland, and Main Street U.S.A. For ten points, identify this animator and namesake of \"Land\" and \"World\" theme park complexes in California and Florida.", "answer": "Walt <b><u>Disney</u></b> (or Walter Elias <b><u>Disney</u></b>; accept <b><u>Disney</u></b>land and Walt <b><u>Disney</u></b> World; accept Walt <b><u>Disney</u></b> Concert Hall)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Architecture"}, {"question": "This territory is home to a namesake petrel, also known as the Cahow [[KAY-how]], which was thought to have been extinct for three hundred years until its rediscovery in 1951. While en route to Jamestown, George Somers\u2019s shipwrecked fleet used smaller boats to colonize this island. During the English Civil War, this island's governor, William Sayle, moved its anti-royalist inhabitants to the Bahamas. For ten points, identify this overseas British dependency that names a \u201cTriangle\u201d known for odd disappearances.", "answer": "<b><u>Bermuda</u></b> (accept <b><u>Bermuda</u></b> Triangle)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "The length of the case <em>Swidler & Berlin v. United States</em>, a case involving this man's administration, led to the demise of the independent counsel at the federal level. Kenneth Starr exonerated this man, but not his wife, in the so-called \"Travelgate,\" which dealt with the sudden firing of seven employees in an act of cronyism. Linda Tripp leaked intimate phone calls between a White House intern and this man, leading to perjury charges and an impeachment trial. The Whitewater and Lewinsky scandals rocked the administration of, for ten points, what Democratic president?", "answer": "Bill <b><u>Clinton</u></b> (or William Jefferson <b><u>Clinton</u></b>; accept William Jefferson <b><u>Blythe</u></b> III)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "One psychologist used his experiences in one of these places to outline his theory of logotherapy. One philosopher controversially claimed that keeping a positive outlook was necessary for survival in these places in the book <em>Man's Search for Meaning</em>. One of the primary developers of these places was used as an example of the \"banality of evil\" in Hannah Arendt's book <em>Eichmann in Jerusalem</em>. Victor Frankl wrote about his time in, for ten points, what locations where the majority of killings during the Holocaust took place?", "answer": "Nazi <b><u>concentration camps</u></b> (accept <b><u>Konzentrationslager</u></b>; accept <b><u>Extermination camps</u></b>; accept <b><u>Death camps</u></b>; accept <b><u>Killing centers</u></b>; accept specific examples like <b><u>Auschwitz</u></b>; prompt on \"prisons\" or \"camps\")", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Psychology"}, {"question": "One god who appeared as one of these animals, Orochi, was defeated by the hero Susano'o [[soo-SAH-nah OH]], who found the \"Grass-Cutting Sword\" in its tail. A traditional symbol of medicine, the Rod of Asclepius, depicts these creatures, which were allowed to freely crawl near patients in Ancient Greece. One legend claims conquistador Hernan Cortes was mistake for Quetzalcoatl, a \"feathered\" example of, for ten points, what type of reptile, which supposedly tempted Adam and Eve in the Garden of Eden?", "answer": "<b><u>Snake</u></b>s (accept <b><u>Serpent</u></b>s; accept <b><u>Dragon</u></b>s before \"Asclepius\" is mentioned)", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {"question": "This individual\u2019s tweet about receiving the COVID-19 vaccine was branded by Ted Cruz as \u201cgovernment propaganda.\u201d Nearly 50 years earlier, this character was seen receiving an injection in a public service campaign to get more children vaccinated against measles. NASA invited this character to join the Challenger flight to teach kids about space, and Mitt Romney said that he loves this character, despite wanting to cut taxpayer money from PBS. From 1969 to 2018, Caroll Spinney portrayed, for ten points, what <em>Sesame Street</em> character, an eight foot-tall avian?", "answer": "<b><u>Big Bird</u></b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "This agreement was first put forward by James Wilson to bridge support for the House of Representatives. Alexander Hamilton asked, \"Would it be just to impose a singular burden, without conferring some adequate advantage?\" in debating this agreement. This compromise proposed \"adding to the whole Number of free Persons, including those bound to Service for a Term of Years, and excluding Indians not taxed.\" For ten points, name this 1787 compromise over the method by which enslaved persons would be counted in determining a state's population.", "answer": "<b><u>Three-Fifths</u></b> Compromise", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "Along this structure, a dispute over the repatriation of Magyar POWs led in part to the Revolt of the Czechoslovak Legion. Alexander Kolchak's government was weakened when parts of this structure between Chita and Krasnoyarsk [[krass-nuh-YARSK]] were destroyed by partisans. Until the completion of the Circum-Baikal Railway, a train ferry was used to connect two parts of this route. Major cities on this route include Yekaterinburg [[yeh-KAT-eh-rin-burg]] and Novosibirsk [[noh-voh-see-BEERSK]]. For ten points, name this longest railway in the world, stretching from Moscow to Vladivodstok.", "answer": "<b><u>Trans\u2013Siberian</u></b> Railway (or <b><u>Transsibirskaya</u></b> magistral; or <b><u>TSR</u></b>; accept \"Railroad\" in place of \"Railway\")", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}, {"question": "The Process Certification Scheme named for this city aimed to prevent a certain good from being sold to finance paramilitaries. Esau Damon was the first person to discover that good, a precious mineral, in Colesberg Kopje, located in this city. The Honoured Dead Memorial in this city commemorates soldiers who died during a Boer War-era siege of this city over its valuable mines. For ten points, name this South African city known worldwide for its diamonds.", "answer": "<b><u>Kimberley</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "This woman and six of her children were killed by members of the Siwanoy tribe during Kieft\u2019s War. Governor Henry Vane often attended meetings hosted by this woman, who eventually settled on Aquidneck [[ah-KWID-nehk]] Island. Mary Dyer was the only person to stand up for this woman when she was tried in Boston in connection with the Antinomian Controversy. For ten points, name this early American religious reformer who was expelled from the Massachusetts Bay Colony for her heretical views.", "answer": "Anne <b><u>Hutchinson</u></b> (or Anne <b><u>Marbury</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "A movement to expand legal rights for these people was opposed by the \"Brunswick clubs\" and was largely financed by \"forty-shillingers\" in an association founded by Richard Shiel and Daniel O'Connell. An 1829 Relief Act benefiting these people was championed by the Duke of Wellington. The \"emancipation\" of these people removed the requirement to renounce transubstantiation before taking civil office. For ten points, name this group that was discriminated against in England with the slogan \"No Popery.\"", "answer": "Roman <b><u>Catholic</u></b>s (accept <b><u>Papist</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This region was the site of the 1872 salvage hearings of the American merchant brigantine, <em>Mary Celeste</em>, after it was mysteriously discovered adrift off the Azores. The failed plan of Nazi Germany to capture this region during World War II was referred to as \"Operation Felix.\" According to Article X [[TEN]] in the Peace of Utrecht, Spain ceded Minorca and this region to Great Britain. Located in the Iberian Peninsula, for ten points, what region on the southern tip of Spain has a namesake rock?", "answer": "<b><u>Gibraltar</u></b> (accept Rock of <b><u>Gibraltar</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "During this event, William Hodson ordered the execution of three princes at the \u201cBloody Gate.\" Colin Campbell reinforced a garrison during this event, which allowed for an evacuation of women and children from Lucknow. Bahadur Shah II was exiled to Burma following this event, which was initiated by a controversy over animal fat used in rifle cartridges. For ten points, identify this 1857 \"Mutiny\" that resulted in the British Crown taking control of India from the British East India Company.", "answer": "<b><u>Sepoy</u></b> Mutiny (or <b><u>Sepoy</u></b> Rebellion; or <b><u>Indian Rebellion of 1857</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "In an event in this year, a politician told one group, \u201cI am the past, you are the future. I embrace you.\u201d During that event in this year, a ten percent real wage increase was secured in the Grenelle [[greh-NEHL]] Agreements. During this year, the Action Programme secured greater freedom of speech in a country that championed the slogan \u201csocialism with a human face.\u201d A series of student protests in France occurred in this year in which Alexander Dubcek [[DOOB-chek]] oversaw the Prague Spring. For ten points, name this year in which European newspapers published accounts of the death of Martin Luther King, Jr.", "answer": "<b><u>1968</u></b> (prompt on \"'68\")", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<b><u>This leader lost one election due to the Otsego sheriff\u2019s office being vacant. As</u></b> <b><u>governor of New York, this man rejected a gerrymandering proposal from Alexander</u></b> <b><u>Hamilton. This leader argued for undivided government in Federalist Paper Number</u></b> <b><u>(+)</u> 2. On the Supreme Court, this leader established the \u201ccases and controversies\u201d precedent, in contrast to the more activist philosophy of John Marshall. A 1795 (*) </b>treaty between the U.S. and the UK is named for, for ten points, what first Supreme Court Chief Justice?", "answer": "John <b><u>Jay</u></b> (accept <b><u>Jay</u></b>'s Treaty)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This man accepted twenty thousand marks as part of an agreement with an</u></b> <b><u>English royal known as the Treaty of Le Goulet [[goo-LEH]]. This man decided to take</u></b> <b><u>an overland route through the Alps rather than a sea route from Marseille [[mahr-</u><u>SAY]] before reconvening with another group in (+)</u> Messina. Isabella of Hainault [[ay-NOH]] was married to this man, who defeated an army led by Otto IV at a battle fought in Flanders in 1214. This victor at Bouvines [[boo-VEEN]] (*) </b>allied with Richard the Lionheart during the Third Crusade. For ten points, name this French king given the epithet \u201cAugustus.\u201d", "answer": "<b><u>Philip II</u></b> of France (or <b><u>Philip Augustus</u></b>; accept \"Philippe\" in place of \"Philip\")", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>One U.S. author, whose parents fled this country, wrote</u> </b><em><b><u>The Pearl That Broke</u></b></em> <em><b><u>Its Shell</u></b></em><b><u> before running for Maryland's 6th congressional district. An author born in</u></b> <b><u>this country wrote a \"mother-daughter story\" in which Mariam kills Rasheed with (+)</u></b> <b>a shovel to save the relationship of Laila and Tariq [[tah-REEK]]. A violent Communist coup in this country inspired a novel in which Assef sexually assaults the Hazara boy, Hassan. Khaled Hosseini (*) </b>set <em>The Kite Runner</em> in, for ten points, what country, ruled by the Taliban?", "answer": "Islamic Emirate of <b><u>Afghanistan</u></b> (or D\u0259 <b><u>Af\u0121\u0101nist\u0101n</u></b> Isl\u0101m\u012b Im\u0101rat; or Im\u0101rat-i Isl\u0101m\u012b-yi <b><u>Afgh\u0101nist\u0101n</u></b>)", "metadata": "Literature - World Literature - Long Fiction"}, {"question": "<b><u>The sacred fire in this non-Greek deity\u2019s temple was extinguished by</u></b> <b><u>Theodosius I in 394 AD. In a festival celebrating this deity, a donkey was dressed in a</u></b> <b><u>garland of flowers as it was believed that the same animal saved the deity from the</u></b> <b><u>god Priapus [[pry-AY-pus]]. (+)</u> Offerings to this deity often included a sacred bread called the \"mola salsa.\" At this deity\u2019s temple, mothers (*) </b>arrived barefoot and left offerings in exchange for blessings. For ten points, name this Ancient Roman goddess of the hearth who was attended to by namesake \"Virgin\" priestesses.", "answer": "<b><u>Vesta</u></b> (accept <b><u>Vesta</u></b>l Virgins)", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {"question": "<b><u>Up to sixty percent of this syndicate's membership is made up of a former</u></b> <b><u>untouchable group known as the</u> </b><em><b><u>Burakumin</u></b></em><b><u>, or \"hamlet people,\" according to</u></b> <b><u>journalist David E. Kaplan. Grave offenses by members in this organization result in</u></b> <em><b><u>Yubitsume</u></b></em><b><u> [[yoo-bit-SOO-meh]], (+)</u> or the ritual cutting off of one's own little finger. Citing their own </b><em><b>ninkyo</b></em><b> honor code, this general class of crime (*) </b>organizations delivered supplies to those affected by the 2011 T\u014dhoku catastrophe. The Japanese word for \"gangsters\" is used to refer to, for ten points, what array of crime organizations in Japan?", "answer": "<b><u>Yakuza</u></b> (accept [a]<em>Gokud\u014d</em>[/a]; accept ; accept [a]<em>Ninky\u014d dantai[/a]</em>)", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Other Social Science"}, {"question": "<b><u>Conrad Reed sparked one of these events in Cabarrus County in 1799. The folk</u></b> <b><u>song \u201cMursheen Durkin\u201d recounts the story of a participant in one of these events.</u></b> <b><u>Many participants in one of these events traveled to it via the Siskiyou (+)</u> Trail. One of these events was publicized in Samuel Brannon\u2019s California Star newspaper and was kickstarted by a (*) </b>discovery made by James W. Marshall. For ten points, identify these types of events, one of which famously occurred following an 1849 discovery at Sutter\u2019s Mill.", "answer": "<b><u>Gold Rush</u></b>es (accept Carolina <b><u>Gold Rush</u></b>; accept California <b><u>Gold Rush</u></b>; prompt on answers relating to the discovery of \"gold\")", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>In 2021, this island used commemorative coins to celebrate its 140th</u></b> <b><u>anniversary of giving some women the right to vote in 1881. This island was ceded by</u></b> <b><u>Magnus VI [[the Sixth]] of Norway to Alexander III of (+)</u> Scotland under the Treaty of Perth in 1266. This island\u2019s legislature, the Tynwald [[TIN-wahld]], claims to be the \u201coldest continuous parliament\u201d in the world, celebrating its millennium in (*) </b>1979. Known in recent history for its tax-haven status and money-laundering controversies, for ten points, what is this island crown dependency located between Great Britain and Ireland?", "answer": "Isle of <b><u>Man</u></b> (or <b><u>Man</u></b>nin; or Ellan <b><u>Van</u></b>nin)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This historian asked \"Why were patricians not permitted to live on the</u></b> <b><u>Capitoline?\" as the ninety-first in a series of</u> </b><em><b><u>Questions</u></b></em><b><u> in one of his works. A set of</u></b> <b><u>\u201cSayings of Spartans\u201d was collected by this one-time priest at the Temple of (+)</u> Delphi in a work which also contains an often-cited account of Egyptian burial rites, the </b><em><b>Moralia</b></em><b> [[moh-RAH-lyah]]. This author is best known for a work containing 48 biographies which are grouped into (*) </b>pairs featuring one Greek and one Roman. For ten points, name this Roman historian who wrote <em>Parallel Lives</em>.", "answer": "<b><u>Plutarch</u></b> (or <b><u>Ploutarch</u></b>os; accept <em><b><u>Plutarch</u></b>'s Lives</em>)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This man's consort may have sent Suppiluliuma I [[soo-pee-loo-LYOO-muh</u></b> <b><u>\"the First\"]] a letter while he besieged Carchemish in a possible effort to merge her</u></b> <b><u>royal house with that of the Hittite (+)</u> Empire. That queen, Ankhesenamun [[ahn-keh-sen-ah-MOON]], was one of the children of Akhenaten, as was this ruler, who may have died from complications of sickle cell anemia. (*) </b>Howard Carter discovered the tomb of, for ten points, what boy-king, found in the Valley of the Kings?", "answer": "King <b><u>Tut</u></b> (or <b><u>Tut</u></b>ankhamen)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}